Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Professional correspondence-subject files
  - Holmwood, Donald, See Video documentary on Alexander Charters. Holmwood also wrote or co-wrote several bibliographies and other items; for these, see the Writings series.
  - Home Economics proposal, Syracuse Area, circa 1974; multiple annotated drafts of "A model for lifelong integrated education in home economics in the Syracuse area" and "Survey of community agencies with adult education related programs, Syracuse city school district" (Box 98)
  - Horton, Myles, See Highlander Center.
  - Houle, Cyril O., 1949-1950; 1956,; 1965-1972,; 1976,; 1978,; 1983,; undated; includes biographical sketch; two brochures, the Cyril Houle Award and the Cyril Houle Scholars in Adult and Continuing Education program; reprint of paper, "The use of print in adult educational agencies"; letter from son David Houle (Box 98)
  - Howard, Arthur H. ("Ham"), 1948-1951; 1967; table design, with Kori Associates (Box 98)
  - Hughes, John (New York state senator), 1968 (Box 98)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, See Johnson, Lyndon B.
  - Hunsaker, Herbert, 1973 (Box 98)
  - Hutchinson, E.M.
    - Correspondence, 1966-1968; 1972,; 1974,; 1977 (Box 98)
    - Comparing Adult Education Worldwide, typescript, annotated; partial, begins with chapter II (Duke); 2 folders (Box 98)
    - Comparing Adult Education Worldwide, typescript, clean copy; 2 folders (Box 98)
    - Comparing Adult Education Worldwide, typescript, clean copy (Box 99)
  - H, miscellaneous (Box 99)
  - IBM, 1964 (Box 99)
  - Illich, Ivan, 1969-1971; includes several essays, speeches and articles by Illich as well as the transcript of a lengthy interview with him (Box 99)
  - Ilsley, Paul, 1986; 2004; includes book chapter, "Adult education departments in the entrepreneurial age" (Box 99)
  - Imel, Susan, See ERIC.
  - Inclusion Times, 1993; disability newsletter, two issues (Box 99)
  - India study tour, 1975; related to a trip by adult educators to India; may have been sponsored by Syracuse University (Box 99)
  - Indian Adult Education Association, 1965-1967; 1975,; 1977; S.C. Dutta; J.L. Sachdeva (Box 99)
  - Indian Journal of Adult Education, 1973; 1984 (Box 99)
  - Indigenous Knowledge (IK), See Mpambo conference.
  - Information Center on Instructional Technology (ICIT), 1973-1974 (Box 99)
  - Institut Canadien de l'education des adultes (L'ICEA), 1963-1965; 1994,; 2000,; 2003 (Box 99)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE), See Multi-Regional Project on Adult and Continuing Education.
  - Institute of Management and Production (IMP), See Gordon, Hopeton L. A.
  - Instituto Internacional de Andragogica, See International Institute for Andragogy.
  - Instituto Nacional para la Educacion de los Adultos, 1982-1983; Miguel Alonzo (Box 99)
    See also Mexico, general; Mexican Association for Continuing Education.
  - Integrative Learning Systems, Inc. / Intellearn, See Martel, Laurence D..
  - Inter-American Adult Education Seminar, organized by Myles Horton; See Highlander Center.
  - Interamerican Federation for Adult Education (FIDEA), 1969; 1979,; 1982,; 1985-1992,; 1995; Felix Adam, others (Box 99)
  - International Adult and Continuing Education Hall of Fame
    - Bylaws, 2008 (Box 99)
    - Correspondence, 1994-2013; mostly about nominees, ceremonies, fundraising; 3 folders (Box 99)
    - Inductee information, Charters (Box 100)
    - Inductee information, others (Box 100)
    - Newsletters, 2008-2011; gaps (Box 100)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, brochures, printouts of Wikipedia and web pages, etc. (Box 100)
    - Programs, 1996; 1998,; 2002,; 2004-2009,; 2011; from induction ceremonies; 2 folders (Box 100)
    - Strategic plan, 2007 (Box 100)
  - International Advisory Committee on Out of School Education, See UNESCO: International Advisory Committee on Out of School Education.
  - International Associates in Adult Education (IAAE), International Associates is part of ICAE and was sponsored in the US by CAEO
    - About the organization, informational brochures, list of members' research areas, etc. (Box 100)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1998 (Box 100)
    - Directories, 1988; 1993,; undated; undated one includes "index of interest areas" (Box 100)
    - Meeting minutes, 1978-1995; many gaps; includes some CAEO information (Box 100)
    - Newsletters, 1982-1995 (many gaps) (Box 101)
    - Planning documents, action plans, vision, Charters' notes (Box 101)
    - Profile sheets, undated; list of organizations and their "international interests and involvements" (Box 101)
    - Survey of CAEO's international activities (Rivera, Ast, Coleman) (Box 101)
    - Tours, miscellaneous information on international tours, classes, etc. offered by a variety of institutions; countries mentioned include Finland, China, Denmark, Canada, USSR, East Africa, Hong Kong, Japan, etc. (Box 101)
  - International Association for Continuing Education and Training (IACET), 1991; 1993,; 1996,; 2000; conference programs, newsletter, general member information, copy of report "A practical handbook for assessing learning outcomes in continuing education and training" by (Box 101)
  - International Association of Evening Student Councils (IAESC), 1964; 1967 (Box 101)
  - International Association for National Youth Service (IANYS), 2000; two copies of program for 6th global conference, one in Spanish and one in English (Box 101)
  - International Biographical Centre, 2000-2001; British version of Who's Who; correspondence, proof copies of entry on ANC (Box 101)
  - International Biography of Adult Education, 1982-1983; ANC was a consultant on the project (Box 101)
  - International Bureau of Education (IBE), See UNESCO: International Bureau of Education (IBE).
  - International Center of Syracuse (ICS)
    - Correspondence, 1968; 1972,; 1976,; 1979,; 1982,; 1984,; 1988-1989,; 1992,; 2000,; 2002; some pertains to a Mr. Rashid who stayed with the Charterses, arranged by ICS (Box 101)
    - International Broadcasters seminar, 1981; 1985 (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous, material from other organizations: copy of International Adult Education Exchange and Cooperation Directory (AERC), publicity brochure from International League for Social Commitment in Adult Education (Box 101)
  - International Conference on Adult Education (CONFINTEA), Several of these took place; see UNESCO: Conferences.
  - International Conference on Comparative Adult Education, First, 1966; University of Exeter
    - About, Foreword (possibly to a report about the conference), purpose, definitions (Box 101)
    - Charters notes, handwritten notes relating to the conference (Box 101)
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 101)
    - Program, 1966 (Box 101)
    - Working papers, 1966; multiple copies of working papers 1, 2 and 3 from different countries, primarily Canada and India but also others (Box 101)
    - Working papers, 1966; 2 folders (Box 102)
    - Miscellaneous papers, three papers: Comparative adult education: Some questions or problems to be resolved (Kidd); Adult education research for a changing world (McGrath); A French experiment in continuing education (Siegle) (Box 102)
    - Miscellaneous, fragments, individual sheets, etc. (Box 102)
  - International Conference on e-Learning (ICEL), 2002 (Box 102)
  - International Conference on the History of Adult Education
    - 3d, 1990; See Hebrew University of Jerusalem.
    - 4th, Strobl (Austria), 1992 (Box 102)
    - 6th, Jena (Germany), 1996; correspondence, opening remarks by Martha Friedenthal-Haase, group photograph of attendees, etc. (Box 102)
    - 8th, Pecs (Hungary), 2000; call for papers only (Box 102)
    - 9th, Leiden (Netherlands), 2002; program, papers, list of participants; many items suffered water damage at some point and are rippled and/or stained (Box 102)
    - 10th, Helsinki (Finland), 2005; program, papers (Box 102)
  - International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE)
    - About the organization, articles of incorporation, brochure, printed pamphlet about founding members, letterhead, history, etc. (Box 102)
    - Conferences
      - Sagamore, 1960; includes a number of position papers (Box 103)
      - World, First, 1965; includes grant request from UNESCO for funding (Box 103)
      - European regional, 1972 (Box 103)
      - World, Third, 1976 (Box 103)
    - Constitution, bylaws, 1962-1968; undated (Box 103)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1963; includes J. Roby Kidd, A. A. Liveright, W. J. McCallion, Arnold Hely, Sydney Raybould, Frank Jessup, UNESCO, M. A. Deleon, Thurman White, Edwin K. Townsend Coles, John Melling, Chris Duke, Amrik Singh, Lalage Bown, John Morris, more; 4 folders (Box 103)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1979; includes a few photographs; 6 folders (Box 104)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1991; undated; 2 folders (Box 105)
    - Meeting minutes, 1960-1976; 1982-1985; 2 folders (Box 105)
    - Membership lists, applications, 1963-1971; undated (Box 105)
    - Proposals
      - African Institute, Ibadan (Lalage Bown), 1962 (Box 105)
      - Inter-American workshops (National Council of Women of the United States), circa 1965 (Box 105)
      - International Fellowship for Continuing Education, circa 1963 (Box 105)
      - People's College Plan, 1964; funding for five "people's colleges" in Southern communities (Box 105)
      - Study tours, various, 1962; 1965; Latin America; Europe (Box 105)
      - US/UK study commission on part-time degrees, including television and correspondence work (Box 105)
    - Publications
      - Bulletin, 1988-1994; twice-yearly review (Box 105)
      - Journal, 1966; 1977; 2 issues, miscellaneous material (Box 106)
      - Newsletters, 1961-1979; 3 folders; gaps (Box 106)
      - Miscellaneous, list of publications, brochure from Sagamore conference, list of universities and colleges engaged in adult education, Occasional Paper #1: French universities (Caldwell) (Box 106)
    - Reports
      - On conferences, 1962-1964; American conference on universities and the quest for peace (Lima, Peru); University adult education in Nigeria (University of Ghana); International seminar on workers and adult education (Israel); U.K. visits (Box 106)
      - On ICUEA activities, 1984; undated; Program of staff training and development (Beatty) (Box 106)
      - On study tours, 1965; UNESCO, Yugoslavia, United Kingdom (Pappert) (Box 106)
      - Miscellaneous, Federal program supporting lifelong learning (Christoffel); An adult education program for Latin America (Haygood, Liveright); Promotion of workers in industry (Cavalli); Paradigm for a new professional association for continuing higher education (speech, author unknown); untitled, on history of adult education in U.S.; Group study tour as an instrument in adult education (UNESCO); Observations on the development of the field of higher adult education in 1965 (author unknown) (Box 106)
    - Miscellaneous, participant lists for unnamed events, 1960-1962 budget information, printed material from other organizations, etc. (Box 107)
  - International Cooperation in Scientific and Technological Research Involving the University, Industry and Government, 1980; seminar, co-arranged by SU and University of Florence; includes lengthy memo by Umberto Colombo on the seminar's organization and content (Box 107)
  - International Correspondence School, 1967 (Box 107)
  - International Council for Adult Education (ICAE)
    See also International Associates in Adult Education (IAAE); Memorabilia: Photographs: ICAE.
    - About the organization, brochures, drafts of incorporation articles, notes on membership, histories, UN form describing, statement of purpose, etc. (Box 107)
    - Conferences
      - Tanzania, 1976; participant list, budget, list of papers presented (Box 107)
      - Paris, 1982; brochure; report, "Actions taken by ICAE relating to the 1982 Paris conference" (Box 107)
      - World Assembly, 3d (Buenos Aires), 1985; programmer, facts sheets, participant list (Box 107)
      - World Assembly, 4th (Bangkok), 1990; participant list, clippings (Box 107)
      - World Assembly, 5th (Cairo), 1994; correspondence, programme, papers, proceedings, reports, etc.; 2 folders (Box 107)
      - World Assembly, 6th (Ocho Rios), 1999; Ocho Rios Declaration, strategic plan, participant handbook, minutes, reports, proceedings (Box 107)
      - World Assembly, 7th (Nairobi), 2007; draft programme (Box 108)
    - Constitution, bylaws (Box 108)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1989; 6 folders (Box 108)
    - Correspondence, 1990-2003; 2006-2008,; 2011-2012,; undated (Box 109)
    - Directories, 1974; 1985,; 1995,; 1996,; 1998 (Box 109)
    - Document exchange plan, 1971-1974; undated; correspondence, drafts of misc. documents, etc.; 2 folders (Box 109)
    - Executive committee members, board members, officers, miscellaneous lists, most undated (Box 109)
    - Meeting minutes, 1973-1976; includes board, executive committee, financial, etc (Box 109)
    - Meeting minutes, 1977-1982; 1993,; 1995; includes board, executive committee, financial, etc (Box 110)
    - Membership lists, applications, includes some participant lists from unnamed events (Box 110)
    - Publications
      - Catalogue of Information Literacy Resources, 1992-1993 (Box 110)
      - Convergence, information about the journal (publicity, editorial guidelines), no issues (Box 110)
      - ICAE News, 1973-1978; 1988-2002; 2 folders (Box 110)
      - ILSS Newsletter, 1993-1994 (Box 110)
      - News from the Secretariat, 1982-1986 (Box 110)
      - Newsletter, 1973-1978 (Box 110)
      - Pachamama, 1996-2001 (Box 110)
      - Voices Rising, 2001-2003; 2007-2009 (Box 110)
      - Miscellaneous, single issues of a few other newsletters; Udaipur Declaration; The Right to Learn; lists of publications; etc. (Box 111)
    - Reports
      - Annual, 1974-1979; 1997 (Box 111)
      - ICAE evaluation discussion paper, 1994 (Box 111)
      - Financial, miscellaneous (Box 111)
        See also meeting minutes; many meeting minutes include financial reports and summaries.
      - Participatory research project, 1977 (Box 111)
      - Relationship with ICUAE (written by ICUAE), 1978 (Box 111)
      - Secretary General's Reports, 1974; 1981-1982,; 1984 (Box 111)
      - Seven year plan, 1996; includes numerous documents summarizing ICAE's goals, activities, future, etc. (Box 111)
      - Women's education: An annotated bibliography, 1993 (Box 111)
      - Miscellaneous, Topics are: Adult education and youth; Basic principles for treatment of prisoners; ICAE's history project; Latin American programs; Lifelong Learning Act of 1974; Meetings in Nordic countries (1977); Missions to Japan, China, Vietnam Russia, West Germany; Environmental thematic working group from CONFINTEA V; Zambia educational reform and continuing education (Box 111)
    - Miscellaneous, includes handwritten notes by Charters, printed material from other organizations, participant lists for unidentified conferences/events, some UNESCO material, etc. (Box 111)
  - International Council for Correspondence Education (ICCE), 1977-1978; includes program from 11th World Conference (Box 111)
  - International Council for Distance Education (ICDE), 1985; 1994; mostly printed material and form letters (Box 111)
  - International dimension of adult education, bibliography/reading list (Box 112)
  - International Education Year (IEY), See UNESCO: International Education Year (IEY).
  - International Encyclopedia of Education, prospectus; See also Writings: Provision in the United States. (Box 112)
  - International expert meeting on comparative studies in adult education, See Denmark conference.
  - International Graduate School
    - About the organization, catalog, information on World University system, publicity, etc. (Box 112)
    - Accreditation Self-Study, 1986 (Box 112)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1987; 3 folders (Box 112)
    - Evaluation, 1982 (Box 112)
    - Evaluation, 1984 (Box 112)
    - Evaluation, 1986; includes rebuttal/response from IGS (Box 112)
    - Financials, 1981-1987 (Box 112)
    - Meeting minutes, 1982-1986 (Box 113)
    - Proposals, includes both administrative (staffing, advertising, accounting) and academic (workshops, seminars, master's in international education, internship program) (Box 113)
    - Reports and papers, Student's eye view of an eternal doctoral program's first-year summer residency functioning (Harty); Discussion paper on operational premises; Syllabus for "Education Futures" seminar 704 (Box 113)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 113)
  - International Handbook of Resources for Educators of Adults, For final published edition, see related collection SUPCE: MSS 33.
    - Comments, Roger de Crow, 1979 (Box 113)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1978; 1985-1986; includes Paul Bertelsen, others (Box 113)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977; requests for copies (Box 113)
    - Cover design (Box 113)
    - Drafts
      - Abstracting services section (Box 113)
      - Organizations section (Box 113)
      - Periodicals section (Box 113)
      - Full copy, Jan 1986 (Box 113)
      - Full copy, Aug 1986; UNESCO document (Box 113)
      - Full copy, Aug 1986; UNESCO document (Box 114)
    - Introduction, outlines (Box 114)
    - Items in the Pamphlet File: Descriptive Subject Headings #97 (Charters, Dengel, Lee) (Box 114)
    - Shipment lists (Box 114)
    - Subject access to adult education books (Charters, Smith, Atherton), 1976; outline of process, project (Box 114)
    - Update packets 1 through 6, 1977-1980; 5 and 6 are complete but for the others, only the cover sheets are present (Box 114)
    - Working notes, handwritten and typed notes, drafts, etc.; 2 folders (Box 114)
  - International Harvester, University of Chicago training program; includes two 8x10 group portraits of "Chicago Central School for Sales Personnel General Line Blockmen Class No. 5 9/9/46 - 10/4/46" sections I and II, with list of names, Alexander Charters among them (Box 114)
  - International House / International House Association (IHA), 1946; 1950-1952,; 2003; includes ANC's membership cards (Box 114)
  - International Institute for Adult Literacy Methods, 1973-1977; 1995; Tehran, Iran (Box 114)
  - International Institute for Andragogy, 1980; 1985,; 1993-1995,; undated; includes issue of Revista de Andragogia and 50+ page explanatory booklet about the organization (Box 114)
    See also Adam, Felix; International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE): Conferences: Slovenia.
  - International Institute for the Unification of Private Law (UNIDROIT), 1993-1996; printed matter only (Box 114)
  - International Intercultural Center (IIC)
    - Correspondence, 1984; general (Box 114)
    - Correspondence, 1985; 2 folders; general (Box 115)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985; responses from query to organizations regarding internships/exchanges (Box 115)
    - Proposal to World University, 1984 (Box 115)
    - Seminars and workshops, 1981-1995 (Box 115)
  - International Platform Association (IPA), 1965; 1972; mostly form letters (Box 115)
  - International programs, direct grants, undated (Box 115)
  - International Society for Adult Education (ISAE), mention of Montreal declaration (Box 115)
  - International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE)
    See also precursor organization, Committee for Study and Research in Comparative Adult Education (CSRCAE).
    - About, 1999; draft of paper by Joost Reischmann (Box 115)
    - Conferences
      - Slovenia, 1998; sponsored by Slovene Adult Education Centre
        - Papers, A-H, Besnard, Boucouvalas, Choi, Henschke (Box 115)
        - Papers, J-T, 2 folders; Jelenc, Jutte, Kalman, Kranjnc, Lee, Maroti, Morris, Siddiqui, Toth (Box 116)
        - Programme, abstract (Box 116)
        - Report on (Charters), co-authored by Margaret Charters; includes some memorabilia (Box 116)
        - Miscellany, travel information, etc. (Box 116)
      - St. Louis, 2002; pre-conference, before AAACE meeting (Box 116)
      - Bamberg, 2006; no actual conference material, just information about the conference (Box 116)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1997; Marcie Boucouvalas, Michal Bron, Joost Reischmann, Dusan Savicevic, John Henschke, others (Box 116)
    - Correspondence, 1998-2013; undated; Marcie Boucouvalas, Michal Bron, Joost Reischmann, Dusan Savicevic, John Henschke, others; 4 folders (Box 117)
    - Membership lists, applications, biographical sketches, 1993; 1998,; undated (Box 117)
    - Seminar, Methods of comparative andragogy, Bamberg, 1995; includes papers, miscellany; 2 folders (Box 117)
    - Website, Feb 2000; printout of contents (Box 118)
  - International Standing Conference for the History of Education (ISCHE), 1990; 1993-1995; includes conference material; issues 19, 20, 21 of newsletter (Box 118)
  - International Task Force on Literacy (ITFL), 1990; includes large poster of "Call to Action" for International Literacy Year (Box 118)
  - Interview questions, unidentified (Box 118)
  - Iran, general, 1977; list of contacts (Box 118)
  - Ironside, Diana, 1977; 1987,; 2000; Ontario Institute for Studies in Education (OISE); includes letter from her sister after her death (Box 118)
  - Israeli, Eitan, 1990-1993; Hebrew University of Jerusalem (Box 118)
    See also Osman, John.
  - I, miscellaneous (Box 118)
  - Jackson, Alvin F., 1964; reprint of article, "The professor as corporate solicitor" (Box 118)
  - Jacques, Joseph, 1971-1973; regarding oral history project, jobs (Box 118)
    Joseph Jacques Interviews
  - James, David, 1971-1972; 1987; National Council of Adult Education (NCAE) (New Zealand) (Box 118)
  - James, Waynne, 2002 (Box 118)
  - Japan, Ministry of Education, Science and Culture, 1981; report, "Life-long education: Report of the Central Council for Education" (Box 118)
    See also Okamura, Seiichi.
  - Japan International Christian University (JICU), 1950; 1966-1967; Maurice Troyer, others (Box 118)
  - Japanese National Commission for UNESCO, 1966; report, "Development of adult education in Japan" (Box 118)
  - Jarvis, Peter, 1983; 1987,; 1995-1997,; 2002; University of Surrey; includes paper, "Learning: The key to the 21st century" (Box 118)
  - Javitz, Jacob K., 1968; U.S. Senator (Box 118)
  - Jayagopal, Raja, 1993; 1995,; 1999; University of Madras (Box 118)
    See also Asian Network on Comparative Adult Education (ANOCAE); World Conference on Comparative Education, Ibadan, Nigeria: Papers, J-O.
  - Jelenc, Zoran, 1983; 1991-1993; University of Ljubljana (Box 118)
    See also Associated Research Centers in Adult Education (ARCAE); International Society for Comparative Adult Education (ISCAE): Conferences: Slovenia; Slovene Adult Education Center.
  - Jessup, Frank, 1964; 1966-1968,; 1972-1974,; 1979,; undated; University of Oxford; University of Oklahoma; includes booklet, "Wolfson College Oxford: The early years" by Jessup (Box 118)
  - Johnson, A. A., See University of Delhi.
  - Johnson Foundation, See Wingspread Conference.
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1965-1968; includes handwritten anecdote about meeting President Johnson, his comments on loyalty and hard work (Box 118)
  - Jossey-Bass, 1972; 1978,; 1981-1982,; undated; a few letters, mostly printed material about their publications (Box 118)
    See also Comparing Adult Education Worldwide (above), of which they were the publisher.
  - JUNTO, 1983-1997; 2001,; 2003,; undated; University of Georgia project; includes correspondence with Jerry Hargis, Gretchen Bersch, others, and printed lists of JUNTO recordings then held by Bird Library (Box 118)
  - J, misc (Box 118)
  - Kallen, Horace, 1967; paper, "The adult individual, higher education, and the future" (Box 118)
  - Kalman, Yaron, See Hebrew University of Jerusalem.